♪In the face of turmoil♪
♪ดื่มน้ำค้างแข็ง♪
♪Your roots hold firmly♪
♪กำรากของท่านไว้แน่น♪
♪To this piece of land♪
♪แผ่นดินผืนนี้♪
♪Chasing after the waves♪
♪ไล่ตามคลื่น♪
♪My leaves flutter across♪
♪ใบไม้ของข้าพัดผ่าน♪
♪The horizon♪
♪ชายแดนหมื่นลี้♪
♪Gazing from afar♪
♪เหม่อมองกันแสนไกล♪
♪At the end of the world♪
♪สุดฟากฝั่งคือ♪
♪Is eternity♪
♪ชั่วฟ้าดินสลาย♪
♪When we meet and then part♪
♪เมื่อพบกันแล้วลาจาก♪
♪When we rely on each other and then drift apart♪
♪เมื่ออิงแอบแล้วห่างไป♪
♪I have never forgotten♪
♪ข้าไม่เคยลืม♪
♪As the glinting of swords cut♪
♪พรายเงาดาบแสงกระบี่♪
♪Through the mottled sky♪
♪วาดผ่านรอยด่างของท้องฟ้า♪
♪The falling dreams♪
♪ฝันที่ตกลง♪
♪Shatter in the wind♪
♪แหลกสลายกลางสายลม♪
♪As the wind breaks through the waves♪
♪ฝ่าลมโต้คลื่น♪
♪It watches thousands of sails cross♪
♪มองนาวานับพันข้ามฟาก♪
♪The vast land and the boundless sea♪
♪ทะเลทุ่งนาแปรเปลี่ยน♪
♪Armor and red robes flying high♪
♪ชุดทหาร ชุดสตรี ลอยฟ่อง♪
♪In the face of bitterness, intense emotions, and joyful adventure♪
♪เคยดื่มน้ำแข็ง โลหิตไม่เย็น ฝันที่จะท่องทุ่งเล่อโหยว♪
♪I only wish you to be by my side♪
♪ปรารถนาเพียงท่านอยู่ข้างกาย♪
♪Making the most of what life offers♪
♪ไม่ผิดต่อแสงวสันต์♪
♪Like towering trees with interconnected roots, I'll accompany you to the ends♪
♪ต้นไม้สูงเสียดฟ้า รากประสาน ท่องไปสุดหล้าเคียงท่าน♪
♪Watching fireflies land on our shoulders♪
♪ดูหิ่งห้อยเกาะบนไหล่เราสอง♪
♪No regrets, no doubts in this world♪
♪ไม่เสียใจในโลกีย์♪
=Wonderland of Love=
=พสุธารักเคียงใจ=
=Episode 26=
=ตอนที่ 26=
Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
Through my secret investigation, I didn't notice anything strange
ข้าแอบตามสืบมาแล้ว
in Lord Xin's Residence.
ไม่ได้มีความผิดปกติอะไร
The usage of vegetable oil, sesame oil,
โดยเฉพาะน้ำมันพืช น้ำมันงา
firewood and coal
ฟืนแห้ง ถ่าน และอื่น ๆ
doesn't differ much from the usual usage.
ปริมาณการใช้ไม่ได้แตกต่าง
I also checked Lord Xin's account
อีกอย่างข้าก็ตรวจสอบบัญชี
with the oil and coal suppliers
ของจวนอ๋องซิ่นในร้านขายน้ำมัน
in previous years
และร้านขายถ่านกับร้านต่าง ๆ
and compared it with the kitchen and woodshed.
เทียบกับห้องครัวแล้วก็ห้องฟืน
Everything seems normal.
ไม่มีอะไรผิดปกติเลย
If there was no fuel for combustion,
แสดงว่าไม่มีเชื้อเพลิงสำหรับการเผาไหม้
why would the fire be so strong?
แล้วทำไมถึงไฟไหม้ขนาดนั้นได้
This is so strange.
นี่มันน่าแปลกเกินไป
Exactly.
ใช่
I also investigated the servants in the residence.
ข้าก็สืบจากคนในจวนแล้ว
However,
สืบไปสืบมา
I still didn't find any clue.
ข้าไม่พบ
Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
See what Wan'niang brought you.
ดูสิว่าหว่านเหนียงเอาอะไรมาให้
Nanny, why are you here?
แม่นม ท่านมาได้อย่างไร
Next time, send someone to inform me.
คราวหน้าถ้าจะมา
I'll go over.
ข้าไปเองก็ได้
It's just a short distance.
แค่ไม่กี่ก้าวเอง
I can still walk.
ข้ายังเดินไหว
Wan'niang purposely went to Xiangji Temple
หว่านเหนียงตั้งใจไปที่วัดเซียงจี
and requested the Heart Sutra
ขอหฤทัยสูตรที่เจ้าอาวาส
which the abbot copied by hand.
คัดลอกด้วยตนเองมาหนึ่งเล่ม
It is believed
ว่ากันว่า
that offering the Heart Sutra before ancestral tablets
ถวายหน้าป้ายวิญญาณของผู้วายชนม์
is the best way to accumulate blessings
เป็นการสะสมพรและกำจัดกรรม
and eliminate karma.
รวมถึงการสั่งสมบุญได้ดีที่สุด
We are here to give it to you
วันนี้ตั้งใจนำมาให้
so that you can offer it in front of Madam Liu's tablet.
ให้ท่านได้นำไปวางไว้ หน้าป้ายวิญญาณของพระนางหลิว
Thank you.
ขอบคุณ
(Heart Sutra)
(หฤทัยสูตร)
Nanny.
แม่นม
Let me put it for you.
ข้าช่วยปักธูปให้ท่านเอง
Beware of the fire.
ท่านระวังจะลวกโดนมือเอา
What happened?
เกิดอะไรขึ้น
I wasn't paying attention just now.
เมื่อครู่ข้าไม่ทันระวัง
I accidentally burnt a hole in the embroidered portrait.
เผลอทำให้ภาพปักเป็นรูโดยไม่ได้ตั้งใจ
What should I do?
จะทำอย่างไรดี
This is all my fault.
นี่เป็นความผิดของข้าจริง ๆ
It's all right.
ไม่เป็นไร
It's just a tiny hole.
แค่รูเล็ก ๆ เอง
Miss Gu, you don't have to blame yourself.
คุณหนูกู้ไม่จำเป็นต้องตำหนิตัวเอง
However, this is Madam Liu's portrait.
นี่เป็นภาพปักของพระนางหลิว
It's all my fault for being careless.
เป็นความผิดข้าที่ไม่ระวังให้ดี
Miss.
คุณหนู
Since you burnt a hole in the embroidery,
ในเมื่อถูกเผาเป็นรูเล็ก ๆ
why don't you fix it?
แค่ซ่อมมันก็ได้แล้วมิใช่หรือ
You are such a nimble-fingered person.
ท่านฝีมือเป็นเลิศถึงเพียงนั้น
Last time, I accidentally dirtied
พัดกลมสีขาวเมื่อคราวก่อน
the white silk fan.
ถูกข้าเผลอทำเลอะ
Then, you embroidered a butterfly on it.
ท่านก็ปัก
It was so exquisite.
ประณีตงดงามมากเลย
The stain couldn't be seen at all.
ดูไม่ออกเลยสักนิดเดียว
Your Highness,
ท่านอ๋อง
please allow me to take the portrait down
ให้ข้าเชิญภาพปักลงมา
and fix the embroidery.
ซ่อมแซมสักหน่อยเถิดนะ
Shiqi,
สือชีหลาง
hurry up and take it down.
ท่านรีบเอาภาพลงมาเร็ว
Let Wan'niang embroider it here.
ให้หว่านเหนียงซ่อมอยู่ที่นี่เถิด
Miss Gu, sorry to have troubled you.
เช่นนั้นก็รบกวนคุณหนูกู้แล้ว
Your Highness, why did you say so?
เหตุใดท่านอ๋องจึงกล่าวเช่นนี้
I'm just mending what I've done.
หว่านเหนียงแค่แกะหายล้อมคอกเท่านั้น
Your Highness.
พระนัดดา
General Han, it's time to take your medicine.
แม่ทัพหาน ได้เวลาดื่มยาแล้ว
Thank you, Your Highness.
ขอบคุณพระนัดดา
Is your injury
บาดแผลบนตัวของแม่ทัพหาน
getting better?
ดีขึ้นบ้างหรือยัง
It's a lot better now.
ดีขึ้นมากแล้ว
To be honest,
อันที่จริง
from the moment I rescued Your Highness,
ตั้งแต่วินาทีที่ช่วยพระนัดดาเอาไว้
I felt my injury
ข้าก็คิดว่าบาดแผลเหล่านี้
was not serious at all.
ไม่เป็นไรตั้งนานแล้ว
I also didn't expect
ข้าก็คิดไม่ถึงว่า
that I would see you again.
จะยังได้พบแม่ทัพหานอีก
When I was
ในตอนนั้น
taken captive by Sun Jing,
ที่ข้าถูกซุนจิ้งลักพาตัวไป
I thought
ข้าก็คิดว่า
I must die with integrity if I really had to.
แม้จะตายก็ต้องตายอย่างสมศักดิ์ศรี
I must not
จะทำให้
bring disgrace to the Li's family.
ลูกหลานสกุลหลี่ของเราขายหน้าไม่ได้
I never thought that I would be rescued.
ไม่คิดเลยว่าจะได้รับการช่วยเหลือด้วย
After we have rescued you,
วันนั้นหลังจากที่ช่วย พระนัดดารัชทายาทเอาไว้
we were in a hopeless dilemma.
พวกเราก็เข้าตาจน
Fortunately, Lord Qin's subordinates
โชคดีที่ลูกน้องของอ๋องฉิน
found us and informed Consort Xiao.
หาเจอและแจ้งกับพระชายาเซียวเฟย
Her Highness allowed us to stay here for a few days.
พระนางให้พวกเราพักอยู่ที่นี่สักระยะ
The situation in the capital is complicated.
สถานการณ์ในเมืองหลวงซับซ้อน
The Cui family relied on their military power
สกุลชุยถือว่าตนเองมีอำนาจทหาร
just like how Sun Jing used to be.
เกรียงไกรเท่ากับซุนจิ้งก่อนหน้านี้
Although His Majesty is your uncle,
ถึงแม้ท่านอ๋องจะเป็นท่านอาของท่าน
there are also people with vile characters around him.
แต่รอบตัวก็ยังมีคนต่ำช้า
Lord Xin and Lord Qi
อ๋องซิ่น อ๋องฉี
are the current emperor's own sons.
ล้วนเป็นโอรสสายตรงของฝ่าบาท
How they would see you
พวกเขาจะคิดอย่างไรกับท่าน
is still unclear.
ก็ยังไม่ชัดเจน
Humans are born intrinsically with a good and similar nature.
แรกเริ่มคนเรานั้น มีความดีเป็นพื้นฐาน
However, their natures will change based on what they learn.
สันดานคล้ายใกล้ วิถีแตกต่างจึงห่างไกล
If a child does not receive proper education, his good nature will change.
หากปราศจากการอบรมสั่งสอน อุปนิสัยย่อมเปลี่ยนไป
The way to educate a child well is through total commitment and devotion.
การศึกษาคือวิถีทางออก สำคัญที่ใจมุ่งมั่นแน่วแน่
Mencius' mother shifted three times to find the best place to bring up her son.
ย้อนมองแม่เมิ่งจื้อครั้งบุราณกาล เฝ้นหาเพื่อนบ้านแลที่อยู่อาศัย
Once Mencius was absent from school, she cut the cloth she was knitting.
ลูกไม่ใฝ่ร่ำเรียนแม่เสียใจ จึ่งตัดด้ายบนกี่ทอสอนสั่งลูก
Have you got used to living here?
คุ้นเคยกับที่นี่หรือไม่
In the private school,
ในสำนักศึกษาเอกชน
many children are coming in and out.
เด็กเข้าออกมากมายทุกวัน
The fact that we are hiding here
พวกเราซ่อนตัวอยู่ที่นี่
won't be noticeable.
จะได้ไม่เป็นที่สังเกต
This place is good.
ที่นี่ดีมาก
When I heard the sound of reading yesterday,
เมื่อวานได้ยินเสียงท่องตำรา
I felt at ease.
รู้สึกสบายใจมากเลย
I've been hearing about private schools.
ข้าได้ยินสำนักศึกษาเอกชนมานาน
Now that I'm here,
บัดนี้พอมาถึงที่นี่ถึงเพิ่งรู้ว่า
I finally know what a private school looks like.
ที่แท้สำนักศึกษาเอกชนก็เป็นเช่นนี้
It is good that Your Highness
พระนัดดาชื่นชอบการเรียนตำรา
likes studying.
นี่เป็นเรื่องดี
I want to study more and learn more skills
ข้าอยากเรียนตำราให้มากขึ้น เรียนรู้ทักษะให้มากขึ้นอีก
so that my mother will feel happy
เช่นนี้เมื่อเสด็จแม่เจอข้า
when she sees me.
ถึงจะรู้สึกมีความสุข
I've grown taller.
ข้าตัวสูงกว่าก่อนหน้านี้อีก
I've also learned more knowledge compared to the past.
ก็ต้องเพิ่มเติมความรู้
It's all my fault for being careless.
เป็นความผิดข้าที่ไม่ระวัง
This type of silk is highly flammable.
ไหมชนิดนี้ติดไฟง่ายที่สุด
Just a short contact with the incense stick could cause a hole.
แค่ธูปแตะโดน
Even the golden threads beneath were damaged.
แม้แต่ด้ายทองด้านในก็เผาจนขาด
Authentic golden threads like this would shrink to small beads
ด้ายทองแท้ชนิดนี้
when they are burnt and broken.
ก็จะย่อเหลือเม็ดเล็ก ๆ
They are not like silk threads
ไม่เหมือนกับด้ายไหม
that can be connected again.
ที่สามารถเชื่อมต่อใหม่ได้
The entire thread has to be removed to redo the embroidery.
ทำได้เพียงนำออกมาทั้งเส้น แล้วปักใหม่เท่านั้น
No wonder you asked me to get this type of golden thread.
มิน่าท่านถึงได้ให้ข้าสั่งคน
I didn't know a small bundle like this could weigh this much.
คิดไม่ถึงว่ามัดเล็ก ๆ แค่นี้
The golden threads taken from the Department of Clothing
ด้ายทองที่นำมาจากแผนกเย็บปัก
have premium quality.
เป็นด้ายทองที่ดีที่สุด
That is why they weigh so much.
ย่อมมีน้ำหนักอยู่แล้ว
Speaking of this,
จะว่าไปแล้ว
a few years ago, the late emperor
ไม่กี่ปีก่อนอดีตฮ่องเต้เคยมีพระบัญชา
banned the commoners from doing embroidery using golden threads.
ห้ามไม่ให้ผู้คนใต้หล้าปักอาภรณ์ทอง
Everyone didn't dare to break the law.
ทุกคนย่อมไม่กล้าฝ่าฝืนพระบัญชา
Hence, they pasted
ดังนั้น
gold foil
พวกเขาจึงนำแผ่นทอง
on the silk.
ติดลงบนผ้าไหม
These are not considered embroidery using golden threads.
จึงไม่ถือเป็นการปักอาภรณ์ทอง
Instead, these are gilded clothes,
แต่เป็นการแปะทองที่อาภรณ์
so, it wasn't against the law.
ไม่ถือเป็นการฝ่าฝืนพระบัญชา
In recent years, it has been quite popular in the capital.
หลายปีมานี้
Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋อง
You said
เมื่อครู่ท่านบอกว่า
this type of silk is highly flammable.
ไหมชนิดนี้ติดไฟง่ายที่สุดหรือ
Yes.
ใช่แล้วล่ะ
If a lot of such silk were put together,
เช่นนั้นหากนำไหมจำนวนมาก
wouldn't they be
มาวางไว้ด้วยกัน
as flammable
จะไม่เป็นการ
as the oil chamber?
ติดไฟง่ายดั่งเช่นโรงน้ำมันหรอกหรือ
Of course.
แน่นอนอยู่แล้ว
I heard that at silk fabric shops in the capital, there are high walls
ข้าได้ยินว่า
and large tanks filled with water outside the storeroom
ล้วนก่อกำแพงสูง
just in case their neighboring shops catch fire.
เพราะกลัวเพื่อนบ้านเรือนเคียง เกิดไฟไหม้ขึ้นมา
Otherwise, everything would be burned
มันก็จะเผาจนราบคาบจริง ๆ
and nothing could be retrieved.
กู่อย่างไรก็กู่ไม่กลับแล้ว
Your Highness, are you all right?
ท่านอ๋อง ท่านเป็นอะไรไปหรือ
Just now, you also said
เมื่อครู่ท่านยังบอกว่า
that people in the capital usually wear gilded clothes
ในเมืองหลวงล้วนใส่อาภรณ์ติดแผ่นทอง
and they paste gold foils on the fabric.
ติดแผ่นทองบนผ้าไหมทั้งนั้น
Yes.
ใช่
Although it's only a thin film,
ถึงแม้จะเป็นแผ่นทองบาง ๆ ชั้นเดียว
having it on the clothes gives it a brilliant look.
แต่เมื่อติดลงไปจะเปล่งประกายอร่าม
It looks really nice.
ดูดีเป็นอย่างยิ่ง
When a real golden thread catches fire,
ทันทีที่ด้ายทองคำแท้สัมผัสไฟ
it shrinks to a small size.
ก็จะหดเป็นเม็ด
When a real gold film catches fire,
เช่นนั้นแผ่นทอง
the same happens.
ก็ใช้หลักเดียวกัน
Your Highness, what are you thinking?
ท่านอ๋อง ท่านคิดอะไรอยู่หรือ
Nothing.
ไม่มีอะไร
Miss Gu.
คุณหนูกู้
I just remembered that I need to
จู่ ๆ ข้าก็นึกเรื่องสำคัญ ขึ้นมาได้เรื่องหนึ่ง
tell Pei Yuan something important.
จะบอกกับเผยหยวน
Please excuse me.
ขอตัวก่อน
Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
Why are there some golden beads
ดินที่ขุดออกมาจากหลังเรือน
in the soil taken from the backyard of Lord Xin's Residence?
ของจวนอ๋องซิ่น
Go and check
ไปตรวจสอบหน่อย
whether the people in Lord Xin's Residence
ในจวนอ๋องซิ่น
bought gilded silk in bulk recently.
ผ้าไหมติดทองจำนวนมากหรือไม่
Gilded silk?
ผ้าไหมติดทอง
Also,
แล้วก็
investigate the confidants
พวกคนสนิทของอ๋องซิ่น
of Lord Xin.
ตรวจสอบมาให้ข้าด้วย
Check whether they have also purchased gilded silk.
ว่ามีการซื้อผ้าไหมติดทอง
All right.
ได้
Young Master.
คุณชาย
A news from the secret agent.
สายลับรายงานมา
Lieutenant He, with only a troop of men,
นายกองพากองกำลังมาแค่หน่วยเดียว
is coming in Xichang's direction.
มุ่งหน้ามาทางเมืองซีฉางแล้ว
Is she coming to the capital?
นางจะเข้าเมืองหลวงหรือ
She doesn't look like she plans to.
ดูท่าทางไม่เหมือน
They are moving quite slowly.
เดินทางช้ามาก
It's as if she's waiting
เหมือนกับว่า
for someone.
รออะไรอยู่มากกว่า
She's probably waiting for Li Ni.
นางกำลังรอหลี่นี่กระมัง
Her infatuation for Li Ni
นางอุตส่าห์รักเขาแท้ ๆ
will most probably be left unanswered.
เกรงว่าหลี่นี่จะทำให้ผิดหวังเสียแล้ว
Li Ni is such a pedantic person.
หลี่นี่ผู้นี้
At this point,
จนป่านนี้
he still doesn't dare to tell Ying
ยังไม่กล้าบอกอาอิ๋งสักคำ
that he wants to marry her.
ว่าข้าอยากแต่งงานกับเจ้า
As for Lord Xin and Lord Qi,
อ๋องซิ่น อ๋องฉี
who do they think they are?
นับเป็นตัวอะไรอีก
How dare they imagine marrying Ying?
ยังกล้าที่จะต้องการตัวอาอิ๋ง
Young Master.
คุณชาย
Shall we give them a lesson?
จะให้ลงมือ
There's no need to give the game away.
ไม่ต้องแหวกหญ้าให้งูตื่นหรอก
Yes.
ขอรับ
It's good that Ying is coming out
ในเมื่ออาอิ๋งออกมาจากลั่วหยางแล้ว
from Luoyang.
ก็เป็นเรื่องที่ดี
At least she's no longer with the Cui Army.
อย่างน้อยก็หลุดพ้น
Otherwise,
มิเช่นนั้น
it will be difficult for us to get in on the ground.
พวกเราก็ยากที่จะลงมือ
I have sent people to follow Lieutenant He secretly.
ข้าได้ส่งคน
Pick a good time
เลือกช่วงเวลาดี ๆ
and set up the maze secretly.
แล้วลอบวางค่ายกลอย่างลับ ๆ
Do not let Cui Yi realise.
อย่าให้ชุยอี่สังเกตเห็นได้โดยง่าย
Understand.
เข้าใจแล้ว
Everything is clear now.
ตรวจสอบชัดเจนทุกอย่างแล้ว
Indeed, Lord Xin wanted to harm Consort Xin.
เป็นอ๋องซิ่นที่ต้องการ ทำร้ายพระชายาจริง ๆ
He ordered people to send numerous gilded silk
อ๋องซิ่นใช้การตัดเย็บชุดเป็นข้ออ้าง
to Consort Xin's room for the reason of making clothes.
สั่งคนนำผ้าไหมติดทองจำนวนมาก
Then, fire was set.
เพื่อให้ง่ายต่อการติดไฟ
Furthermore, on the night of the fire,
อีกอย่างในคืนไฟไหม้
they also delayed the rescue process on purpose.
ก็เป็นพวกเขาที่จงใจทำให้การดับไฟล่าช้า
One of them admitted that
แถมหนึ่งในนั้นยังสารภาพว่า
they drugged
พวกเขาวางยาสลบ
the food for Consort Xin
ลงไปในอาหารของพระชายา
and her servants.
กับสาวใช้และคนรับใช้
Therefore,
ดังนั้นในคืนนั้น
none of them woke up that night.
จึงไม่มีใครตื่นขึ้นมา
All of them were burned to death.
ทั้งหมดถูกเผาปิดปากทั้งเป็น
Li Jun!
หลี่จวิ้น
How could he be so vicious?
ทำไมเขาถึงอำมหิตได้ถึงเพียงนี้
Consort Xin was married to him for many years.
พี่สะใภ้ใหญ่อยู่กับเขามาตั้งหลายปี
They had been through difficult times together.
นับว่าเป็นสามีภรรยา ที่ร่วมทุกข์ร่วมสุขกันมา
Now, we have
ตอนนี้ถึงแม้ว่า
witnesses, material evidence,
พยาน หลักฐาน คำสารภาพ
and statements,
ล้วนมีหมดแล้ว
but we still need to identify the witness
ขาดแค่ที่มาของยาสลบ
who knows about the drugging.
ที่ยังจับกุมพยานไม่ได้
Lord Xin is indeed disappointing.
อ๋องซิ่นผู้นี้
Shiqi.
แต่ว่าสือชีหลาง
Do you really plan to report him
เจ้าคิดจะรายงานเขาต่อหน้าฝ่าบาท
in front of His Majesty?
จริง ๆ หรือ
Ever since Consort Dong passed away,
หลังจากพระชายาต่งสิ้นพระชนม์
only Consort Xin cared for me.
มีเพียงพี่สะใภ้ใหญ่ที่ห่วงใยข้าดูแลข้า
She died so unjustly.
นางตายอย่างไร้ความยุติธรรมเช่นนี้
I must seek justice for her
ข้าจะต้องทวงความเป็นธรรมให้นาง
in front of His Majesty.
ต่อหน้าฝ่าบาทแน่นอน
- Long Live Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาททรงพระเจริญ หมื่นปีหมื่นปีหมื่นหมื่นปี
Please rise.
เงยหน้าขึ้นได้
- Thank you, Your Majesty.
ขอบพระทัยฝ่าบาท
Where is Lord Qin?
อ๋องฉินเล่า
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
Lord Qin said he had urgent military affairs.
อ๋องฉินบอกว่ามีกิจการทหารเร่งด่วน
He left the capital early in the morning,
ออกจากเมืองแต่เช้า
so he could not make it to the morning meeting.
มาไม่ทันเข้าเฝ้า
He asked me to request a day's leave from Your Majesty.
จึงให้กระหม่อมขอลาฝ่าบาทพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
He always claims to have military affairs to handle,
มีแต่กิจการทหารทั้งวัน
as if he is the only
ทำเหมือนกับว่ามีแค่เขาคนเดียว
busy person.
ที่มีงานต้องทำ
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Cui Yi submits a letter
ชุยอี่เขียนหนังสือมา
stating that he is willing to marry his daughter to the prince.
กล่าวว่ายินดีให้บุตรสาว อภิเษกกับองค์ชาย
I think
กระหม่อมคิดว่า
this matter should be confirmed as soon as possible.
เรื่องนี้ควรตัดสินใจ ตั้งแต่เนิ่น ๆ พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
It's not good to ask Cui Yi
เรื่องนี้ จะไปถามชุยอี่ก็ไม่ค่อยดีเท่าไร
whether he wants to
ฉีอ๋องกับฉินอ๋อง
marry his daughter
ตกลงจะให้ลูกสาว
to Lord Qi or Lord Qin.
แต่งงานกับใครกันแน่
Your Majesty, since Lord Xin is a new widower,
ฝ่าบาท อ๋องซิ่นเป็นพ่อม่ายใหม่
he could marry Miss Cui as well.
อ๋องซิ่นก็สู่ขอสกุลชุยได้เช่นกัน
You have a point.
สิ่งที่เจ้าพูดก็สมเหตุสมผลนะ
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Consort Xin has just passed away
พระชายาอ๋องซิ่นเพิ่งจะสิ้นพระชนม์
not long ago.
เพียงไม่กี่วัน
I do not have the intention to remarry.
ลูกไม่มีกะจิตกะใจ สานต่อความสัมพันธ์จริง ๆ
Lord Xin
อ๋องซิ่นช่างเป็น
is indeed a man with affection and loyalty.
คนมีความรักความจริงใจเหลือเกิน
Why would a man with affection and loyalty
คนมีความรักความจริงใจ
plot a murder against his own wife
จะทำเรื่องไร้ความเป็นมนุษย์ อย่างการวางแผน
and do something extremely tragic?
ลอบสังหารภรรยาของตนเองได้อย่างไร
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Lord Xin first drugged
ก่อนอื่นอ๋องซิ่นวางยาสลบ
Consort Xin and her servants.
พระชายาซิ่น
Then, he placed bundles of silk that are highly flammable in her room
นอกจากนี้ยังกองผ้าไหมที่ติดไฟง่าย
and set the room on fire, making it like an accident.
จงใจวางเพลิง
This caused the death of Consort Xin
ทำให้ไฟครอกพระชายาซิ่นและทุกคนในเรือน
and everyone staying there.
จนเสียชีวิตทั้งเป็น
This is an unfounded accusation!
เจ้าใส่ร้ายป้ายสี
Li Ni! What are you talking about?
หลี่นี่ เจ้าพูดเหลวไหลอะไร
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
I have all the witnesses and evidence.
พยานและหลักฐานทุกอย่างมีครบ
I left the capital early in the morning to investigate this matter.
ที่ลูกออกจากเมืองแต่เช้า
The person who sent the silk
คนที่ส่งผ้าไหมเข้าวัง
and Lord Xin's confidants who did the drugging
และคนสนิทของอ๋องซิ่นที่วางยาสลบ
have been captured by me.
ล้วนถูกข้าจับตัวได้หมดแล้ว
The testimony of the confidants of Lord Xin as well as the evidence
คำสารภาพจากเหล่าคนสนิทของอ๋องซิ่น
have been sent to Dali Temple.
ล้วนถูกส่งไปยังศาลต้าหลี่แล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
He is making an unfounded accusation!
เขาใส่ร้ายลูก
I didn't do it!
ลูกไม่ได้ทำ
I really didn't do any of these!
ลูกไม่เคยทำ
Father, please seek justice for me!
เสด็จพ่อ โปรดตัดสินแทนลูกด้วย
Those witnesses
พยานเหล่านั้น
are all serving in your residence.
ล้วนเป็นคนในจวนของท่าน
Many of them were assigned by His Majesty
หลายคนได้รับการแต่งตั้งจากเสด็จพ่อ
and have been with you since you were young.
ให้ติดตามท่านมาตั้งแต่เด็ก
Jun.
จวิ้นเอ๋อร์
Father!
เสด็จพ่อ ๆ
I really didn't do it!
ลูกไม่ได้ทำจริง ๆ
Why did you do such actions?
ทำไมเจ้าถึงได้ทำเรื่อง
Why?
เพราะอะไร
Someone set me up!
ลูกถูกใส่ร้ายต่างหาก
Father!
เสด็จพ่อ
Please seek justice for me!
โปรดตัดสินแทนลูกด้วย
Consort Xin
พระชายาอ๋องซิ่น
was such a good child with filial piety!
เป็นเด็กกตัญญูมากขนาดไหน
Someone set me up!
ลูกถูกคนใส่ร้ายจริง ๆ
Father!
เสด็จพ่อ
Please seek justice for me!
โปรดตัดสินแทนลูกด้วย
Do you think he could bribe so many people to set you up?
เขาสามารถติดสินบนคนเยอะขนาดนั้น
Most of them
ในหมู่คนพวกนั้นยังมีตั้งหลายคน
are even your confidants!
ล้วนเป็นคนสนิทของเจ้า
Do you think I'm stupid?
เจ้าคิดว่าพ่อโง่หรืออย่างไร
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Lord Xin's action of murdering his own wife
การกระทำของอ๋องซิ่นครั้งนี้ ขัดต่อจริยธรรมของมนุษย์
is totally against humanity.
เรื่องที่ลอบสังหารภรรยาแท้ ๆ นี้
Please give him a serious punishment.
ฝ่าบาทโปรดลงโทษอย่างหนักด้วยพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Father.
เสด็จพ่อ
Take this disobedient son out.
ลากตัวลูกไม่รักดีคนนี้ออกไป
Lock him up in his residence.
กักขังภายในจวนอ๋องซิ่น
He shall not leave the residence.
ห้ามออกจากจวนแม้แต่ครึ่งก้าว
Let him chant sutras
ให้เขาสวดมนต์ขอขมา
and pray for Consort Xin every day
ให้กับพระชายาอ๋องซิ่นทุกวันทุกคืน
to eliminate his karma.
เพื่อขจัดหนี้กรรมที่เขาก่อไว้
Father!
เสด็จพ่อ ๆ ๆ
I didn't do it!
ลูกไม่ได้ทำ
Please seek justice for me!
โปรดตัดสินให้ลูกด้วย
I really didn't do it!
ลูกไม่ได้ทำจริง ๆ
Fa... Father!
เสด็จ เสด็จพ่อ
Father!
เสด็จพ่อ ๆ
Father! I really didn't do it!
เสด็จพ่อ ลูกไม่ได้ทำจริง ๆ
I didn't!
ลูกไม่ได้ทำ
Please seek justice for me!
โปรดตัดสินแทนลูกด้วย
Father! I really didn't do it!
เสด็จพ่อ ลูกไม่ได้ทำจริง ๆ
Father!
เสด็จพ่อ
One day of married life breeds days of enduring affection.
เป็นสามีภรรยาหนึ่งวันมีบุญคุณร้อยวัน
I never thought that Li Jun
ข้าไม่เคยคิดเลยว่า
would murder his wife.
พี่ใหญ่จะลงมือเหี้ยมโหด
Fights between husband and wife and fights between brothers for property
สามีภรรยาทะเลาะกัน
are not uncommon in my hometown.
ไม่ใช่เรื่องแปลกในชนบทของเรา
I didn't expect that someone in the capital
ใครจะไปรู้ว่าที่เมืองหลวงแห่งนี้
would murder
จะมีคนทำเพื่อ
his own wife
แย่งชิงอำนาจ
to fight for power and position.
สังหารภรรยาของตนเอง
How inhuman!
นี่มันไม่ใช่คนเกินไปแล้ว
When Consort Xin first got married,
ตอนที่พี่สะใภ้เพิ่งแต่งเข้ามา
I was the most unwelcome person in the residence.
ในจวนอ๋อง
She knew that I lost my mother since young,
นางรู้ว่าข้าเสียแม่ไปตั้งแต่เด็ก
so she always treated me well.
ตลอดมาดีกับข้ามาก
How could Li Jun
คนที่มีจิตใจเมตตาเช่นนี้
kill a kind person like her?
พี่ใหญ่ก็ยังลงมือได้ลงคอ
Before I came to Xichang,
ก่อนที่จะมาเมืองซีฉาง
I thought this was a lively and happening place.
ยังคิดว่าเมืองหลวงครึกครื้นแบบนี้
I wanted to enrich my experience.
จะได้มองเห็นโลกได้กว้างขึ้น
If I had known that I would experience these incidents,
ใครจะไปรู้ว่าได้เห็น เรื่องตั้งมากมายขนาดนี้
I wouldn't have come.
สู้ไม่มาเลยยังจะดีเสียกว่า
Now, I miss
ตอนนี้ช่างคิดถึง
the mound at Laolan Pass.
เนินดินขรุขระที่ด่านเหลาหลันเหลือเกิน
At that time,
ในตอนนั้น
we suffered
พวกเราพี่น้อง
so much.
หัวเราะเฝื่อนๆ ทุกวัน
We didn't have much money.
เงินก็ไม่ค่อยจะมี
We even had to fight with one another
แม้แต่จะกินแป้งเปล่า ๆ ชิ้นเดียว
just to get a bite of the white bread,
ทุกคนก็ต้องแย่งไปแย่งมา
but our life was so happy.
แต่ชีวิตกลับมีความสุข
Yes.
ใช่
Those days,
ตอนนั้น
we were really happy.
มีความสุขจากใจจริง ๆ
Mister Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
People here in the capital are so unpredictable.
ผู้คนในเมืองหลวงจิตใจยากจะคาดเดา
You once said
เจ้าเคยบอกว่า
that we would go back to Laolan Pass one day.
อีกหน่อยพวกเราจะกลับด่านเหลาหลัน
When will we be going back?
แล้วเมื่อไรเราจะกลับไปกันล่ะ
There are things unsettled yet.
ยังมีเรื่องที่ยังไม่แล้วเสร็จ
When I settle them one by one,
เอาไว้จัดการเรียบร้อยหมดแล้ว
we shall go back.
พวกเราก็จะกลับไปกัน
We won't need to care about
ไม่ต้องสนใจเรื่องปากหวานก้นเปรี้ยว
the intrigues in this capital.
ในเมืองหลวงแห่งนี้อีกต่อไปแล้ว
Let's go.
ไปกันเถิด
(Your Highness, as time goes by,)
(บางทีผ่านไปสักระยะ)
(perhaps you would realise)
(ท่านอ๋องก็จะเข้าใจ)
that you cannot go back
ไม่ใช่ว่าอ๋องฉินคิดจะกลับไปเป็นสือชีหลาง
to Laolan Pass
ที่ด่านเหลาหลัน
as you wish
ก็สามารถกลับไปเป็นสือชีหลาง
and be Shiqi again.
ที่ด่านเหลาหลันได้
As Lord Qin, you cannot escape
แต่เป็นการที่อ๋องฉิน
your role as the crown prince.
จำเป็นต้องเป็นรัชทายาทแห่งตำหนักบูรพา
Mister Shiqi, Taozi sent a letter
สือชีหลาง เถาจื่อส่งข้อความมา
stating that Miss Cui is waiting to meet you at Wonderland.
บอกว่าคุณหนูชุยกำลังรออยู่
Can you submit a report
เจ้าสามารถถวายฎีกาโดยตรง
to the emperor and marry me?
เพื่ออภิเษกกับข้าหรือไม่
Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
Don't you understand?
ท่านยังไม่เข้าใจอีกหรือ
You shall be the crown prince
ข้ากับตำแหน่งตำหนักบูรพา
in order to marry me,
ท่านต้องเหมาทั้งสองอย่าง
otherwise,
มิฉะนั้น
you are left with nothing.
ท่านจะไม่ได้อะไรเลยสักอย่าง
Can't you trust me?
เจ้าจะเชื่อใจข้า
Can you stop forcing me and give me some time?
ไม่บีบบังคับข้า ให้เวลาข้า อีกสักนิดไม่ได้เลยหรือ
Why are you deceiving yourself and others?
ทำไมท่านต้องหลอกตัวเองด้วยล่ะ
Then why did you come and meet me?
แล้วทำไมเจ้าถึงมาพบข้า
Indeed.
ใช่
Everything went like what you have expected.
ทุกอย่างเป็นอย่างที่เจ้าคาดคิด
What else do you want to do?
เจ้ายังต้องการอะไรอีก
I'm not here to laugh at you.
ข้าไม่ได้จะมาเยาะเย้ยเจ้านะ
I know that you must be upset
ข้ารู้ว่า
seeing your loved one do something like this,
ท่านจะต้องโศกเศร้ามาก
so I just want to check on you.
ดังนั้นข้าแค่อยากจะมาดูท่านเท่านั้นเอง
Indeed.
ใช่
He could do that
นางเป็นภรรยาที่สมรสกับเขาแท้ ๆ
to his wife.
เขาก็ยังทำเช่นนั้นได้
It's the Eastern Palace,
นั่นเป็นตำหนักบูรพา
it's the position of the crown prince.
เป็นตำแหน่งผู้สืบบัลลังก์
Power can make a person frenzied.
ดังนั้นอำนาจ
That's why I don't want the position!
ดังนั้นข้าถึงได้ไม่ต้องการตำแหน่งนั้น
I've known that it has been a cage since I was young.
ตั้งแต่เด็กข้ารู้ว่า
Do you want our children
เจ้าต้องการให้ลูกของเรา
to be born
อีกหน่อยเกิดมา
in this cage?
ในกรงขังเหมือนกันหรือ
Right.
ใช่
You do know that power could make a person frenzied.
อำนาจจะทำให้ผู้คนสติคลุ้มคลั่ง
With this in mind,
และเป็นเพราะเหตุนี้
do you still want our children
เจ้ายังจะให้ลูกของเรา
to fight with one another
ในอนาคตต้องเข่นฆ่ากันเอง
for this position in the future?
เพื่อแย่งชิงตำแหน่งนี้หรือ
However, you are the emperor's son.
แต่ท่านเป็นโอรสของโอรสสวรรค์
You are Lord Qin who recaptured two capitals.
ท่านเป็นฉินอ๋องที่ยึดคืนสองเมืองมาได้
You are also the commander-in-chief of the famous Zhenxi Army.
และท่านยังเป็นผู้บัญชาการกองทัพเจิ้นซี
Don't you think
ท่านคิดว่าในเวลานี้
you are currently in a cage?
ท่านไม่ได้อยู่ในกรงขังหรือ
I don't mind making myself the bait.
ข้าไม่เสียดายที่จะเอาตัวเป็นเหยื่อล่อ
Can't you tell?
ท่านดูไม่ชัดเจนหรืออย่างไร
I don't want to fight with you.
ข้าไม่อยากทะเลาะกับเจ้าอีกแล้ว
♪If I forget the fleeting of time♪
♪หากลืมแสงหิ่งห้อยที่หายวับไป♪
♪Waiting for memories to shatter and sink♪
♪รอความทรงจำ♪
♪Are the entanglement I find hard to let go of♪
♪ความเกี่ยวพันนั้น♪
♪If longing is not forgotten♪
♪หากความคะนึงหาไม่เคยจางหาย♪
♪I long to return to the very first moment♪
♪กลับไปสู่เวลาแรกด้วยความอาลัย♪
(Don't you understand?)
(ท่านยังไม่เข้าใจอีกหรือ)
(You shall be the crown prince)
(ข้ากับตำแหน่งตำหนักบูรพา)
(in order to marry me,)
(ท่านต้องเหมาทั้งสองอย่างฉ
(otherwise,)
(มิฉะนั้น)
(you are left with nothing.)
(ท่านจะไม่ได้อะไรเลยสักอย่าง)
(Can't you trust me?)
(เจ้าจะเชื่อใจข้า)
(Can you stop forcing me and give me some time?)
(ไม่บีบบังคับข้า ให้เวลาข้า อีกสักนิดไม่ได้เลยหรือ)
♪Despite going against fate I have no regrets loving you♪
♪พลิกผันเหตุและผล♪
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪ยอมตัดความปรารถนาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪As I wait for your answer♪
♪รอเจ้าตอบข้าเสมอ♪
(Tang Confectionery)
(ร้านถังปิ่ง)
Come.
ที่นี่แหละ
Would you like some pastries?
นายท่านทั้งสอง ถังปิ่งสักหน่อยไหม
I want to eat...
ข้าอยากกิน
I want two of these
เอาอันนี้สองชิ้น
and two of these.
แล้วก็อันนี้อีกสองชิ้น
Sure.
ได้เลย ๆ
Ear.
เอ่อร์ตัว
In your opinion,
เจ้าว่า
why did Young Lady
ครั้งนี้คุณหนู
go and meet Lord Qin alone
ทำไมถึงต้องไปพบอ๋องฉินเพียงลำพัง
without bringing me with her?
ไม่ให้ข้าตามไปล่ะ
Is she hiding something from me?
นางมีเรื่องอะไร
That can't be it.
ไม่หรอกกระมัง
Miss Cui treats you so well.
นายกองของเจ้าดีกับเจ้าขนาดนั้น
She won't hide any secrets from you.
นางไม่มีเรื่องปิดบังเจ้าหรอก
Needless to say,
เรื่องนั้นไม่ต้องบอก
she treats me very well.
คุณหนูย่อมดีกับข้ามากที่สุดอยู่แล้ว
Then why didn't she allow me to go with her?
แล้วทำไมนาง
Could it be because
หรืออาจเป็นเพราะว่า
she just wants to meet Mister Shiqi alone?
นางอยากไปหา
It's just like
ก็เหมือนข้า
me wanting to be
ข้าก็อยากอยู่กับเจ้า
with you alone.
ด้วยตัวคนเดียวเท่านั้น
If both Miss Cui
ถ้าเกิดว่านายกองของเจ้า
and Mister Shiqi were around,
กับสือชีหลางอยู่กันหมดละก็
wouldn't it be difficult
เช่นนั้นเวลาเราคุยกัน
for us to talk?
จะไม่อึดอัดแย่หรอกหรือ
Perhaps
บางที
that's what she thought.
นางก็คิดแบบนี้เหมือนกัน
When did you
เวลาเจ้าพูด
become so honey-mouthed?
ปากหวานขนาดนี้ตั้งแต่เมื่อไรกัน
I'm not honey-mouthed,
ข้าไม่ได้ปากหวาน
I'm just telling the truth.
ข้าแค่พูดตามความจริงเท่านั้น
Taozi.
เถาจื่อ
I want to ask you something.
ข้ามีคำถามหนึ่งอยากถามเจ้า
Go ahead.
ถามมาสิ
You haven't answered
คราวก่อน
the question I asked you
คำถามที่ข้าถามเจ้าที่ทุ่งเล่อโหยว
at Wonderland.
เจ้ายังไม่ได้ตอบข้าเลย
Are... Are you...
ตก ตกลงเจ้า
Are you willing to?
ตกลงเจ้ายินดีหรือไม่
You're such a fool.
ตาทึ่ม
If I'm not willing to,
ถ้าหากข้าไม่ยินดีละก็
will I still be sitting here
จะยังนั่งอยู่ตรงนี้
and eating pastries with you?
กินขนมกับเจ้าหรือ
That's true though.
ก็จริง ก็จริง
Eat this.
กินเถิด
It's nice, right?
อร่อยล่ะสิ
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
You're awake.
เจ้าฟื้นแล้วหรือ
Was it you?
เป็นท่าน
I got someone to help you get changed with clean clothes.
ข้าได้สั่งคน
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
It was me
ข้าเป็นคนพาเจ้า
who brought you here.
มายังสถานที่แห่งนี้
Don't worry.
เจ้าสบายใจได้
This place has beautiful scenery.
สถานที่แห่งนี้มีทิวทัศน์สวยงาม
It's just like a paradise.
ราวกับอยู่ในแดนสวรรค์ก็มิปาน
Both of us
พวกเราสองคน
can live here.
ใช้ชีวิตด้วยกันอยู่ที่นี่
We don't have to care about worldly affairs and just relax.
ไม่สนใจทางโลก
There won't be
และจะไม่มีใคร
people coming to disturb us.
มารบกวนพวกเราสองคนอีก
Isn't that a good idea?
ไม่วิเศษหรอกหรือ
What drug did you give me?
ท่านวางยาอะไรข้า
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
You shall not get angry.
เจ้าห้ามโกรธเป็นอันขาดล่ะ
It's not good for your body.
มันจะไม่ดีต่อสุขภาพของเจ้าได้
Your current condition is perfect.
สภาพของเจ้าในตอนนี้ก็ดีมากแล้ว
As long as you obey me,
ขอเพียงเจ้าเป็นเด็กดีเชื่อฟัง
I won't harm you.
ข้าจะไม่ทำร้ายเจ้าอย่างแน่นอน
I won't harm your father as well.
และจะไม่ทำร้ายท่านพ่อของเจ้า
You are a snob who colluded with Jieshuo.
โจรชั่วอย่างท่าน
You even wanted to harm my father.
ยังคิดจะทำร้ายท่านพ่อของข้า
You will be my sworn enemy!
ข้ากับท่านอยู่ร่วมฟ้ากันไม่ได้
Look at you.
เจ้าดูเจ้าสิ
Speak nicely.
พูดด้วยดี ๆ
Why did you get angry?
ทำไมถึงได้โกรธอีกเล่า
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
What do you want to eat later?
อีกสักพักเจ้าอยากกินอะไร
I got them to cook some of your favourite dishes.
ข้าสั่งให้คนทำอาหารจานโปรด
Later, shall we have a meal together?
อีกประเดี๋ยว
Get out of my way.
ไสหัวไปเดี๋ยวนี้
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
From now on,
นับจากนี้ไป
we will eat together
ทุก ๆ วัน
every single day.
พวกเราจะกินข้าวด้วยกัน
I'll be by your side all the time.
ข้าจะอยู่กับเจ้าตลอดเวลา
All right?
ดีไหม
You'll promise me,
เจ้ารับปากข้าอยู่แล้ว
won't you?
ถูกไหม
(Lord Qin's Residence)
(จวนอ๋องฉิน)
Lord Qin.
อ๋องฉิน
Young Lady is missing!
คุณหนูของข้าหายไป
That day, after you said that she had left,
วันนั้นที่ท่านบอกว่านางกลับไปแล้ว
I searched along the route for fear that I went a wrong way.
ข้าก็ค้นหาตลอดทาง
I didn't see her at all even when I reached Luoyang.
จนกระทั่งกลับถึงลั่วหยาง
Great General was worried
แม่ทัพใหญ่ร้อนใจมาก
and he sent people to search for her everywhere but futile.
ส่งทหารออกตามหาไปทั่ว
That's why I came to see you with hope.
ข้าถึงพกความหวังอันน้อยนิด
Where could she have gone to?
ท่านว่าตอนนี้นางจะไปที่ไหนได้
Taozi.
เถาจื่อ
How do you usually find her?
ปกติเจ้าหาคุณหนูของเจ้า
She has been using the same herbal spices since young.
คุณหนูบ้านข้า
I could find her with just a special ingredient,
ข้าแค่ใช้กระสายแบบพิเศษ
but this time,
แต่ว่าครั้งนี้
it didn't work no matter how hard I tried.
ไม่ว่าอย่างไรข้าก็ไม่มีวิธีเลย
This means
แสดงว่า
the person who took her
คนที่ลักพาตัวนางไป
knows these details very well.
ย่อมรู้รายละเอียดเหล่านี้เป็นอย่างดี
That's why he could prepare in advance
ถึงได้เตรียมการพร้อมไว้ล่วงหน้า
so that you wouldn't realise.
ไม่ให้เจ้าพบได้
Then this person is...
เช่นนี้คนคนนี้คือใคร
It's Liu Chengfeng.
คือหลิ่วเฉิงเฟิง
There is a vast terrain between Luoyang
ระหว่างลั่วหยางกับทุ่งเล่อโหยว
and Wonderland.
ภูมิประเทศกว้างใหญ่
There are many dense forests.
มีต้นไม้นับไม่ถ้วน
It's not difficult to hide
หากต้องการซ่อนใครสักคน
a person.
ไม่ใช่เรื่องยาก
If it was really Liu Chengfeng
หากเป็นหลิ่วเฉิงเฟิง
who held Miss Cui captive,
ที่ลักพาตัวคุณหนูชุยจริง ๆ
it would be a big trouble.
เช่นนั้นก็แย่แน่
He probably didn't stay here for too long.
เขาคงไม่กล้าอยู่ต่อนานหรอก
He might have left for somewhere else with Miss Cui.
น่าจะพาคุณหนูชุย
They wouldn't be too far away.
นางไม่ถูกซ่อนไกลเกินไปหรอก
Why?
เพราะอะไรหรือ
Ying is way too smart.
เพราะอาอิ๋งฉลาดเกินไป
If he wanted to go on a long journey together with her,
หากหลังจากลักพาตัวนาง
it would be very difficult to not leave any clues behind.
จะให้ตลอดเส้นทางไร้ร่องรองใด ๆ
Liu Chengfeng is very obsessed with Ying.
หลิ่วเฉิงเฟิงยึดติดในตัวอาอิ๋งลึกมาก
A scheming person like him
ด้วยอุบายในใจของเขา
must have planned in advance
จะต้องจัดสถานที่ที่ปลอดภัย
and found a place near Luoyang to settle down.
เอาไว้ใกล้ ๆ ลั่วอย่างล่วงหน้าก่อนแล้ว
On the map,
แต่ว่าบนแผนที่นี้
there are so many places other than Luoyang.
สถานที่นอกลั่วหยาง
Wouldn't it
ต้องใช้เวลานานแค่ไหน
take a long time to locate her?
กว่าจะหานางเจอล่ะ
The north.
ทางเหนือ
Only the northern parts.
มีเพียงทางเหนือ
Since Liu Chengfeng colludes with Jieshuo,
ในเมื่อหลิ่วเฉิงเฟิงสมคบกับเจียซั่ว
he will definitely choose somewhere
เช่นนั้นจะต้องเลือกสถานที่
that he could get support from the Jieshuo rangers.
ที่ทหารลาดตระเวนของเจียซั่ว
Only the northern area is possible.
เช่นนั้นก็มีเพียงทางเหนือเท่านั้น
The northern area is wide and scarcely inhabited.
ทางเหนือกว้างใหญ่แต่ประชากรเบาบาง
The forest is dense.
มากด้วยป่าทึบ
Most importantly,
ที่สำคัญยิ่งกว่าก็คือ
going a little up north
ไกลออกไปทางเหนือ
is the grassland where the Jieshuo rangers could support.
ก็คือทุ่งหญ้าที่เจียซั่ว
Since we have narrowed down the search area
เช่นนั้น
to just this part,
ขอบเขตก็หดลงเยอะมาก
it will be much easier to look for her.
การตามหานางก็ง่ายขึ้นเยอะ
Let's not waste time.
เวลาไม่คอยท่า
Let's depart now.
พวกเราออกเดินทางทันที
Without the military order, I couldn't deploy the troops now.
ตอนนี้ไม่มีคำสั่งทหารจากราชสำนัก
Chang'er, Bao, we shall disguise ourselves and depart first.
ฉางเอ่อร์ เหล่าเป้า
- Yes.
ได้
Yuan.
อาหยวน
Bring some people to the hunting ground and then catch up with us.
เจ้าพาคนจำนวนหนึ่งไปที่พื้นที่ล่าสัตว์
If anyone asks, tell them we are going hunting outside the city.
ถ้ามีคนถามถึง
I'll do it right now.
ข้าจะไปจัดการเดี๋ยวนี้
How is it?
เป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
We have searched the hills on both sides.
ภูเขาทั้งสองฝั่งค้นหาหมดแล้ว
There's nothing strange.
ไม่มีอะไรผิดปกติ
There are high mountains and it is sparsely populated.
ภูเขาสูงชัน คนก็เบาบาง
It's not easy to find her.
หายาก
Mister Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
I have an idea.
ข้ามีวิธีดี ๆ นะ
What is it?
อะไรหรือ
Last time, we used to occupy a hill and act as the lord.
เดิมทีพวกเราพี่น้อง
We were also worried about the soldiers coming after us.
ก็กังวลว่าจะมีทหาร
Therefore, we would try our best to be secretive in whatever we do.
ดังนั้นปกติเวลาทำอะไร
However, there was
แต่มีสิ่งหนึ่ง
one thing
ที่ไม่ว่าอย่างไร
that we could never hide.
ก็ปกปิดไม่มิด
Every person needs salt
นั่นก็คือคนเรายังมีชีวิตอยู่
to survive.
จะต้องกินเกลือ
People who sell salt
และคนที่ขายเกลือ
wouldn't go
ไม่มีทางที่จะ
deep into the forest.
เดินทางมาถึงป่าลึกเช่นนี้หรอก
To hold Cui Lin hostage,
หากหลิ่วเฉิงเฟิงจะลักพาตัวชุยหลิน
Liu Chengfeng must have many subordinates.
เช่นนั้นลูกสมุนของเขา คงจะมีอยู่ไม่น้อยแน่นอน
This is a remote area.
ที่ทุรกันดารเช่นนี้
Salt sold at townships nearby definitely has a fixed amount.
เกลือที่วางขาย
Commoners
ชาวบ้านธรรมดา
cannot afford salt.
ไม่มีทางได้กินเกลือหรอก
Whenever they buy salt, they would only buy little.
ทุกครั้งที่พวกเขาแลกเกลือ
They won't buy a lot.
ไม่มีทางแลกเยอะอยู่แล้ว
Let's investigate the townships nearby separately.
พวกเราแยกย้ายกันตรวจสอบ
Ask them whether there were any outsiders who came and bought salt
ดูว่าสถานที่ขายเกลือ
at a large amount.
อีกอย่างหากปริมาณไม่น้อย
We could follow up from there.
ก็สามารถตามสืบต่อไป
All right.
ได้
Here.
มา
Drink the medicine.
ดื่มยาก่อนนะ
Don't worry.
เจ้าวางใจได้
This is not poison.
นี่ไม่ใช่ยาพิษ
It's not poison,
ไม่ใช่ยาพิษ
but it's something that could make me feel weak
แต่เป็นยาที่ทำให้ร่างกายข้าอ่อนแรง
so that you could detain me, right?
สะดวกแก่การกักขังข้าใช่หรือไม่
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
I'm doing this for your own good.
ข้าหวังดีต่อเจ้าจริง ๆ นะ
Don't be a hypocrite and tell me all this.
ไม่ต้องมาเสแสร้งพูดเรื่องพวกนี้กับข้า
If you had cared about my feelings,
ตราบใดที่ท่านยัง คำนึงถึงความรู้สึกของข้าสักครึ่งหนึ่ง
you wouldn't have colluded with the Jieshuo people,
ก็ไม่มีทางสมรู้ร่วมคิดกับพวกเจียซั่ว
let alone harming my father.
ยิ่งไม่มีทางคิดที่จะลอบทำร้ายท่านพ่อข้า
I didn't have a choice.
ข้าเองก็ไม่มีทางเลือกเหมือนกัน
If you had married me in the beginning,
ถ้าหากเจ้าแต่งงานกับข้าแต่เนิ่น ๆ
I surely wouldn't have been in contact
ข้าย่อมไม่มีทางยุ่งเกี่ยวอะไรกับ
with the Jieshuo people.
พวกเจียซั่วอยู่แล้ว
I would've
และข้าก็ย่อม
cared for your father as well.
กตัญญูกับท่านพ่อเหมือนกัน
Anyway, it's all right.
แต่ไม่เป็นไร
As long as you're willing to be with me now,
ขอเพียงตอนนี้เจ้าอยู่กับข้า
I feel satisfied.
ข้าก็พอใจแล้ว
No matter how you hit me and scold me,
ไม่ว่าเจ้าจะทุบตีข้าหรือดุด่าข้าอย่างไร
I'll enjoy it.
ข้าก็ยินดีทั้งนั้น
If you refuse to drink it,
ถ้าหากเจ้าไม่ยอมดื่ม
I'll feed it to you.
เช่นนั้นข้าจะป้อนเจ้าเอง
This time, Youren has made great contributions.
ครั้งนี้เจ้าสามสร้างผลงานครั้งใหญ่เลย
We asked around in the county town.
คิดไม่ถึงว่าพอมาถามถึงในเมือง
They said no outsiders ever came to buy salt.
ไม่มีคนต่างถิ่นมาซื้อเกลือเลย
However, at Huanshan County located dozens of li away,
แต่ว่าในตำบลฮ่วนซาน
someone bought
ก่อนหน้านี้พักหนึ่ง
a lot of salt not long ago.
มีคนมาซื้อเกลือไปไม่น้อยเลย
Therefore, the salt in their county
ดังนั้นเกลือที่อยู่ในเมือง
had been sent to Huanshan to be sold there.
ล้วนถูกยืมไปขายที่ตำบลฮ่วนซาน
Don't praise me like that.
พี่รองก็ชมข้าเกินไป
It was pure luck.
แค่ดวงดีน่ะ ดวงดี
Look at him.
เจ้าดูสิ
The salt in Huanshan County was not necessarily bought by Liu Chengfeng.
เกลือในตำบลฮ่วนซานใช่ว่า
How could you say you are lucky?
จะบอกได้อย่างไรว่าตัวเองดวงดี
We haven't started investigating,
ยังไม่ทันสืบเลย
but what if it was him?
เผื่อว่าใช่ล่ะ
- What if it wasn't him? - What if it was him?
เผื่อว่าไม่ใช่ล่ะ
No, I said...
ไม่ใช่ ข้าบอกว่าไม่ใช่ก็ไม่ใช่
Youde.
พี่รอง
No.
เดี๋ยว
Listen to Mister Shiqi.
ฟังสือชีหลางสิ
Let's continue searching
พวกเราแยกย้ายลงมือกันต่อ
every hill separately.
ค้นหาทุกเขา
This area is about a hundred li wide.
รัศมีไม่เกินร้อยลี้
Each of us
พวกเราทุกคน
shall bring more people.
พาคนไปเยอะหน่อย
Bao, stay in the middle as the contact point.
เหล่าเป้า ติดต่อระหว่างทาง
All right.
ได้
Let's go.
ออกเดินทาง
- All right. - Yes!
- ได้
Young Master.
คุณชาย
There seem to be strangers in villages nearby.
ดูเหมือนชนบทใกล้เคียงจะมีคนแปลกหน้า
Our guards outside also saw hoofprints on the ground.
คนสอดแนมที่ส่งออกไปข้างนอก
Li Ni is blamed.
คนสมควรตายอย่างหลี่นี่
Li Ni's nose so sensitive.
จมูกดียิ่งกว่าสุนัขเสียอีก
Now that
ตอนนี้กลับเป็นเขา
he came to me himself,
ที่มาหาถึงที่เอง
this is just right.
ประจวบเหมาะ
I shall capture him
ข้าจะจับตัวเขากับพวกสุนัขรับใช้
and all his henchmen.
ให้หมดในคราเดียว
Then I shall kill them in front of Ying.
จากนั้นก็ฆ่าทิ้งต่อหน้าอาอิ๋งเสียเลย
This is the place.
ที่นี่แหละ
Mister Shiqi, what do we do?
สือชีหลาง ตอนนี้ทำอย่างไรดี
Don't alert them first.
อย่าเพิ่งทำให้แตกตื่น
You go and send the signal.
เจ้าไปส่งสัญญาณ
I'll go in and check out the place.
ข้าจะเข้าไปตรวจสอบดูหน่อย
All right.
ได้
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
What are you looking at?
เจ้าดูอะไรอยู่
You seem to be deeply absorbed in it.
ดูเสียใจลอยเชียว
Look.
เจ้ารีบดูเร็ว
Look at what I've brought you.
ข้าเอาอะไรมาให้เจ้า
I know
ข้ารู้
that you were also upset
คราวก่อนที่ฉางโจว
when our wedding at Changzhou
วิวาห์ของเราถูกก่อกวน
was interrupted.
ข้าเองก็รู้ว่าเจ้าเสียใจมาก
Therefore, this time,
ดังนั้นครั้งนี้
I picked a few
ข้าก็คัดสรรชุดแต่งงาน
wedding gowns for you.
มากมายมาอย่างดี
Choose the one you like.
เจ้าเลือกสักชุดที่เจ้าชอบสิ
Let's have our wedding
แล้วพวกเราก็แต่งงานกัน
happily.
อย่างมีความสุขกันเถิด
Liu Chengfeng.
หลิ่วเฉิงเฟิง
Do you know
ท่านรู้หรือไม่ว่า
what you are doing?
ตัวเองกำลังทำอะไรอยู่
I'm getting ready to get married to you.
ข้ากำลังเตรียมพิธี
You know very well
ทั้งที่ท่านก็รู้อยู่แก่ใจดี
that I won't ever marry you.
ว่าข้าไม่มีวันแต่งงานกับท่านหรอก
You and I grew up together.
ท่านกับข้าเติบโตมาด้วยกัน
I treat you
ข้าเห็นท่าน
like an elder brother.
เสมือนพี่ชายแท้ ๆ
To me,
ในใจของข้า
you are my elder brother.
ท่านก็คือพี่ชายของข้า
Stop it!
พอได้แล้ว
Stop saying things like this
เจ้าไม่ต้องใช้คำพูดพวกนี้
to prevaricate.
บอกปัดข้า
Your father
พ่อของเจ้า
has never treated me like his son.
ไม่เคยเห็นข้าเป็นลูกชายแท้ ๆ
I'm also not
และข้าก็ไม่ใช่พี่ชาย
your elder brother.
ของเจ้าเลยด้วยซ้ำ
It was all because of Li Ni.
ล้วนเป็นเพราะหลี่นี่
If Li Ni hadn't existed,
ถ้าหากไม่มีหลี่นี่ละก็
you would've been married to me already.
เจ้าก็แต่งงานกับข้าตั้งนานแล้ว
You also wouldn't have said
และเจ้าก็ไม่มีทางพูดจา
something so ruthless!
เย็นชาไร้หัวใจเช่นนี้ได้หรอก
Whether there was Li Ni or not, I wouldn't fall in love with you.
มีหรือไม่มีหลี่นี่
Father has asked me a few times
ท่านพ่อเคยถามข้า
whether I want to be married to you.
ว่าข้าอยากแต่งงานกับท่านหรือไม่
He felt that
เขาคิดว่าเราสองคน
since we grew up together,
เติบโตมาด้วยกันตั้งแต่เด็ก
you've been caring for me in every aspect.
ท่านดูแลข้าทุกอย่าง
He was thinking
ท่านพ่อคิดว่า
if he passed away
ถ้าหากมีวันหนึ่ง
one day,
ที่เขาจากโลกนี้ไปแล้ว
would I be lonely
ทิ้งข้าเอาไว้คนเดียว
when I was left all alone?
ข้าจะโดดเดี่ยวหรือไม่
If you could take care of me,
ถ้าหากมีท่านคอยดูแลข้า
he might not need to worry.
เขาอาจจะวางใจได้
However, I told him
แต่ข้าบอกกับท่านพ่อ
that I won't be married to you,
ว่าข้าไม่แต่งงานกับท่านหรอก
or perhaps
หรือพูดอีกอย่างในตอนนั้น
I didn't intend
ข้าก็ไม่ได้วางแผน
to get married at all.
จะแต่งกับใครอยู่แล้ว
However, you submitted a report to the emperor
แต่เจ้ากลับถวายฎีกาให้กับฮ่องเต้
that you wish to marry
ว่าจะเลือกแต่งงานกับหนึ่งใน
one of the three princes.
องค์ชายทั้งสาม
You're lying.
เจ้าหลอกข้า
It's not that you don't want to get married at all.
เจ้าไม่ใช่ไม่อยากแต่งงาน
You don't want to marry me at all.
แต่เจ้าไม่อยากแต่งงานกับข้าต่างหาก
There's no need for me to lie to you.
ข้าไม่จำเป็นต้องหลอกท่าน
At one point, I really didn't have the intention to get married.
มีช่วงหนึ่งที่ข้าไม่อยากแต่งงานจริง ๆ
A female has to face so many difficulties.
สตรีในโลกก็ลำบากเช่นนี้แล
I only live once.
เกิดมาบนโลกนี้
If no one understands me and knows me well,
ถ้าหากไม่มีใครเข้าใจหรือรู้จักข้าดี
why must I be married to someone?
ทำไมข้าจะต้องแต่งงานด้วย
Can't I live happily and freely alone?
ข้าใช้ชีวิตอยู่คนเดียว
Do I not understand you
ข้าไม่เข้าใจเจ้า
and know you well?
ไม่รู้จักเจ้าดีหรือ
You used to respect me
เมื่อก่อนท่านให้เกียรติข้ามาก
and treat me well,
และท่านก็ดีกับข้ามาก
but that was neither understanding me
แต่นั่นไม่ใช่การเข้าใจข้า
nor knowing me well.
และไม่ใช่การรู้จักข้าดี
Before I met Li Ni,
ก่อนที่จะเจอหลี่นี่
I thought
ข้าคิดว่า
it's fine to be alone,
อยู่คนเดียวก็ดีอยู่แล้ว
but after I met him,
แต่หลังจากที่ได้พบกับหลี่นี่
I only want to be with him.
ข้าต้องการอยู่กับเขา เพียงผู้เดียวเท่านั้น
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
My love for you
ข้าชอบเจ้า
has already reached this extent.
ชอบถึงขนาดนั้นแล้ว
Why did you say something like this to hurt me?
ทำไมเจ้าถึงพูดแบบนี้
Is it because
เป็นเพราะว่าข้า
I'm associated with the Jieshuo people?
ผูกมิตรกับพวกเจียซั่วใช่ไหม
Are you mad because of that?
เป็นเหตุทำให้เจ้าโกรธมาก
Do you hate me?
ถึงได้เกลียดข้ามาก
I just want to survive.
ข้าแค่อยากมีชีวิตอยู่ต่อไป
If I die,
ถ้าหากข้าตายไป
will you remember me?
เจ้าจะจำข้าได้ไหม
You won't!
ไม่มีทาง
You'll forget about me immediately!
เจ้าจะลืมข้าทันที
You'll put everything about me behind you!
เจ้าจะทิ้งข้าเอาไว้ข้างหลัง
You'll marry Li Ni
เจ้าจะแต่งงานกับหลี่นี่
and live happily ever after!
จากนั้น
You'll forget about me forever.
เจ้าจะลืมข้าตลอดไป
Therefore, I mustn't die.
ดังนั้นข้าตายไม่ได้
I mustn't die!
ข้าตายไม่ได้
I cannot allow you to marry Li Ni.
ข้าปล่อยให้เจ้าแต่งงานกับหลี่นี่ไม่ได้
That's why I approached the Jieshuo people.
ข้าก็เลยไปหาพวกเจียซั่ว
Young Master.
คุณชาย
This might be the last time
นี่อาจเป็นครั้งสุดท้ายที่ข้า
I'm calling you this.
จะเรียกท่านว่าคุณชายอีก
It's because the elder brother who used to care for me
เพราะพี่ชายที่ข้าเคารพนับถือ
and deserved my respect
ที่เคยรักและปกป้องข้าคนนั้น
is dead.
เขาตายไปแล้ว
He is dead.
เขาตายแล้ว
He died in that river.
เขาตายอยู่ในแม่น้ำสายนั้น
Of course, you have the right
แน่นอนว่าท่านมีสิทธิ์
to choose to survive,
ที่จะเลือกมีชีวิตอยู่ต่อไป
but you approached the Jieshuo people for your survival.
แต่ท่านกลับไปหาพวกเจียซั่ว
You cannot say
ท่านจะมาบอกไม่ได้
that it was all for me!
ว่าที่หาพวกเขาก็เพื่อข้า
After all is said,
พูดไปพูดมา
now everything...
เรื่องทั้งหมดในตอนนี้
seems to be
กลายเป็นความผิด
all my fault.
ของข้าเพียงคนเดียว
Ying.
อาอิ๋ง
How cruel you are.
เจ้าช่างใจร้ายเหลือเกิน
I've done so much for you,
ข้าทำเพื่อเจ้าตั้งมากมาย
but now you make it sound like I have only myself to blame.
ตอนนี้กลับเป็นข้าที่หาเรื่องใส่ตัว
To you,
ในสายตาของเจ้า
you see no one other than Li Ni!
นอกจากหลี่นี่ก็ไม่มีใครคนอื่นอีก
Anyway, it's all right, Ying.
แต่ว่าไม่เป็นไร อาอิ๋ง
No matter what you say,
ไม่ว่าเจ้าจะพูดอย่างไร
you'll never
ชั่วชีวิตนี้
get to see Li Ni anymore in your entire life.
เจ้าก็อย่าคิดจะเจอหลี่นี่อีกเลย
I won't
ข้าไม่มีวันปล่อยให้เขา
let him take you away from me.
แย่งเจ้าไปจากข้างกายข้าได้
You'll surely become my wife.
เจ้าจะต้องเป็นภรรยาของข้า
In your dreams!
ฝันไปเถอะ
Never will I marry you!
ข้าไม่มีวันแต่งงานกับท่านแน่
Not only Li Ni, but also my father and his men
ไม่เพียงหลี่นี่
will come and rescue me.
ต้องมาช่วยข้าแน่นอน
You won't get away from this.
ท่านหนีไม่รอดหรอก
The Cui Army has numerous cavalrymen.
กองทัพสกุลชุยมีทหารม้าหนักนับไม่ถ้วน
You've seen with your own eyes
ท่านเองก็เคยเห็นเองกับตามาแล้ว
how the Cui Army's cavalrymen charge.
ว่าทหารม้าหนักของกองทัพสกุลชุย
My father
ท่านพ่อข้า
will ride a horse here
จะขี่ม้ามาด้วยตัวเอง
and crush your bones.
และบดขยี้กระดูกของท่าน
Mister Shiqi.
สือชีหลาง
Bao is ready.
พวกเหล่าเป้าเตรียมพร้อมแล้ว
Just wait for them to take the bait.
รอแค่เหยื่อติดกับ
Get ready.
เตรียมตัวให้พร้อม
Yes.
ได้
- Yes.
- ได้
Young Master,
คุณชาย
the rangers sent a message.
ทหารลาดตระเวนรายงานมาว่า
At a hundred li away,
ห่างออกไปร้อยกว่าลี้
they saw traces of cavalrymen who might have passed by.
มีรองรอยของกองทัพทหารม้าหนัก
Great General might be approaching us with his cavalry.
แม่ทัพใหญ่คงจะ
If he reaches here with his cavalry,
หากแม่ทัพใหญ่
all the decorations we've put up will be useless.
การเตรียมการของเราในเรือนรับรอง
Furthermore, the cavalry even have armored horses.
อีกทั้งพวกทหารม้าหนัก
When faced with them, our strategy will not work.
กลไกของเรา
They will reach here at the latest by tomorrow noon.
อย่างช้าสุดเที่ยงวันพรุ่งนี้
Young Master.
คุณชาย
Please take our men back to Jieshuo's territory first
ท่านนำคน
using the trail over the mountain.
ถอยกลับไปที่ดินแดนเจียซั่วก่อนเถิด
I will stay here
ข้าจะเฝ้าอยู่ที่นี่
as if you and Lieutenant He are still here.
แสร้งทำเหมือนว่าท่านกับนายกอง
I will hold the Great General off.
ข้าจะถ่วงแม่ทัพใหญ่ไว้ให้เอง
♪If I forget the fleeting of time♪
♪หากลืมแสงหิ่งห้อยที่หายวับไป♪
♪Waiting for memories♪
♪รอความทรงจำ♪
♪To shatter and sink♪
♪แหลกละเอียดจมหาย♪
♪The emotional scars in your heart♪
♪ตกลงบนรอยด่างบนหัวใจเจ้า♪
♪Are the entanglement♪
♪ความเกี่ยวพันนั้น♪
♪I find hard to let go of♪
♪คือสิ่งที่ข้ายากจะตัดใจ♪
♪If longing is not forgotten♪
♪หากความคะนึงหาไม่เคยจางหาย♪
♪I long to return to the very first moment♪
♪กลับไปสู่เวลาแรกด้วยความอาลัย♪
♪The affection we had in our fateful situation♪
♪ความอบอุ่นที่โชคชะตาเคยมี♪
♪How I wish to keep it for you♪
♪อยากเก็บไว้เพื่อเจ้า♪
♪If love still remembers♪
♪หากความรักจำได้♪
♪The promises we made♪
♪เราเคยสัญญา♪
♪Even if this love hurts me♪
♪ต่อให้รักนี้ทำร้ายข้า♪
♪I'll continue living for you♪
♪ก็จะมีชีวิตอยู่เพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Holding onto the memories♪
♪ไปตามเค้าโครงในความทรงจำ♪
♪Waiting is my persistence♪
♪รอคอยคนที่ข้ายึดติด♪
♪If love remembers♪
♪หากความรักจำได้♪
♪The promise I made to you♪
♪สัญญาที่รักษาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Despite going against fate♪
♪พลิกผันเหตุและผล♪
♪I have no regrets loving you♪
♪ไม่เสียใจที่ยืนหยัดรักเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪ยอมตัดความปรารถนาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪As I wait for your answer♪
♪รอเจ้าตอบข้าเสมอ♪
♪If love remembers♪
♪หากความรักจำได้♪
♪The promise I made to you♪
♪สัญญาที่รักษาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪Despite going against fate♪
♪พลิกผันเหตุและผล♪
♪I have no regrets loving you♪
♪ไม่เสียใจที่ยืนหยัดรักเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪ยอมตัดความปรารถนาเพื่อเจ้า♪
♪As I wait for your answer♪
♪รอเจ้าตอบข้าเสมอ♪